Guide to the Duke University Religious Council Records, 1938-1971
Duke University. University Archives
Duke University Religious Council records 1938-1971
Duke University. University Archives
Duke University. Religious Council.
1.5 linear feet Extent: approx. 1200 Items
The Duke University Religious Council was formed in 1956 to coordinate interdenominational religious life and activity on the university campus and replaced the Student Religious Council, formed in 1937. Types of material include correspondence, minutes, annual reports, financial papers, membership rosters, and the Council’s founding documents. Major subjects include committees organized by the Council; special services, programs, and events; national Christian organizations; and documents relating to the council’s community outreach. The material range in date from 1938-1971.
UA.31.04.0010
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advanced notice required for use.
Provenance
The Duke University Religious Council Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer between 1976-1978.
Historical Note
The Religious Council was formed in 1956 to coordinate interdenominational religious activities affiliated with Duke University. In April of 1955, members of the Special Church Board Committee, a sub-committee of the Duke University Church, proposed to create a unified council with a widened sphere of operations. The new council would coordinate and serve as an advisory board to the various campus committees and organizations involved in religious activities. In 1956, to facilitate these goals, the Board of Duke University Church (established in 1938) and the Student Religious Council (formed in 1937) were merged to create the Religious Council. The Religious Council was a committee-based organization with community, faculty, and student representation. However, the Council emphasized student membership on the various committees. The Council also emphasized its interdenominational character, encouraging the participation of all faiths in religious activities.
Collection Overview
This collection contains material created and accumulated by the Religious Council and range in date from 1938-1971. A majority dates from 1950 to 1965. The collection is divided into two series: Administrative Records and Subject Files. The administrative records contain correspondence, annual reports, financial papers, minutes of the executive council, and founding constitution and by-laws. Subject files include the materials accumulated by the Special Observance Committee, which include materials relating to various programs organized by the committee: correspondence, minutes, reports, and printed materials; Religious Emphasis Week, 1943-1955; outreach programs with Edgemont Community Center: reports, correspondence, financial papers, and the Living & Learning Project; and papers relating to the United Christian Council.
Subject Headings
Duke University. Religious Council; Edgemont Community Center (Durham, N.C.); Duke University Church; Duke University. Chapel; Duke University -- Religion; Duke University -- Religious Emphasis Week; Duke University -- Students -- Religious activities; United Student Christian Council
Related Material
Religious Life Reference collection, 1937-present
Duke University Archives
Duke University Church records, 1936-1985
Duke University Archives
Durden, Robert F. The Launching of Duke, 1924-1949. Durham, NC: Duke University Press, 1993.
Contents of Collection
- Administrative Records, 1938-1966
  Annual reports, correspondence, financial papers, founding documents, executice council minutes, and miscellaneous material.
  - Annual reports, 1938-1940 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1966 (Box 1)
  - Financial papers, 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - Founding documents, 1955, 1966, undated (Box 1)
  - Minutes, Executive Committee, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, Executive Committee, 1958-1956 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1948-1956 (Box 1)
- Subject Files, 1943-1971 (Box 1)
  Various committees, programs, community outreach efforts, religious events and services, and national Christian organizations
  - Faculty Program, 1957-1958, undated (Box 1)
  - Research Committee, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Special Observances Committee (SOC), Correspondence, 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - SOC, Correspondence, 1959-1966 (Box 1)
  - SOC, Minutes, 1956-1957, 1961 (Box 1)
  - SOC, The Bishop's Company Repertory, 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - SOC, Marriage Seminar, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - SOC, Printed material, 1957-1965 (Box 1)
  - SOC, Newspaper clippings, 1957-1966 (Box 1)
  - SOC, Publicity fliers and calenders, 1957-1966 (Box 1)
  - SOC, Easter Sunrise Service, 1947-1966 (Box 1)
  - SOC, Good Friday Service, 1943-1971 (Box 1)
  - SOC, Holy Week, 1948-1949, undated (Box 1)
  - SOC, Lentin Service, 1948-1966, bulk 1948-1955 (Box 1)
  - SOC, Noonday Meditation, 1952-1958 (Box 1)
  - SOC, Miscellaneous, 1956-1966 (Box 1)
  - Edgemont Community Center (ECC), Correspondence, 1958-1969 (Box 1)
  - ECC, Financial papers, 1957-1966 (Box 1)
  - ECC, Edgemont Community Classic, 1971 (Box 1)
  - ECC, Living and Learning Project, 1966-1970 (Box 1)
  - ECC, Long-Range Planning Committee, 1966-1967, undated (Box 1)
  - Interdenominational meeting, 1949-1951 (Box 1)
  - Japanese Cherry Tree Planting Service, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Receptions, 1954-1957 (Box 1)
  - Religious Emphasis Week, 1943-1951 (Box 1)
  - Religious Emphasis Week, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Religious Emphasis Week, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Religious Emphasis Week, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Religious Emphasis Week, 1955 (Box 1)
  - School program at Salvation Army Hospital and House, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Student Religious Council, 1952-1957 (Box 1)
  - United Student Christian Council, 1948-1952 (Box 1)
  - Veterans Hospital Ministry, 1960-1961, 1964 (Box 1)
  - World's Student Christian Federation, 1939-1952 (Box 1)
  - World Student Day of Prayer, 1939-1952 (Box 1)
  - United Student Christian Council, 1948-1952 (Box 1)